<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preacht on January 30th, 1683 in Westminster-Abby before the reverend and honourable, the Kings judges, and printed at their request by Edw. Pelling ...</title>
            <author>Pelling, Edward, d. 1718.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53971</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1096</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23221</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12755773</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12755773</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93422</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53971)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93422)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 727:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preacht on January 30th, 1683 in Westminster-Abby before the reverend and honourable, the Kings judges, and printed at their request by Edw. Pelling ...</title>
                  <author>Pelling, Edward, d. 1718.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 43 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H. Hills, Jun. for William Abington ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Romans XIII, 2 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93422:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93422:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHT On <hi>January 30<hi rend="sup">th</hi>.</hi> 1683. IN <hi>Weſtminſter-Abby,</hi> Before the REVEREND and HONOURABLE, the KINGS JUDGES, and Printed at their Requeſt.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Edw. Pelling,</hi> Praebendary of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and Chaplain to his Grace the Duke of <hi>Somerſet.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Omnis quidem ſub Rege &amp; ipſe ſub nulló, ſed tantùm ſub Deo; non eſt inferior ſibi Subjectis, non parem habet in Regno.</p>
               <bibl>Bracton. l 1. c. 8.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>A Deo Rex, à Rege Lex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed by <hi>H. Hills</hi> Jun. for <hi>William Abington,</hi> next Door to the <hi>Wonder Tavern</hi> in <hi>Ludgate-Street.</hi> 1684.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:93422:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93422:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable Sir <hi>George Jeffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes,</hi> Knt. and Bar. Lord Chief Juſtice of
<hi>England,</hi> and one of His Majeſties Moſt Honourable Privy-Council.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Do heartily wiſh, that your Lordſhips deſires had not been ſo Earneſt and Preſſing as they were, to have this Diſcourſe made Publick, which I aſſure Your Lordſhip was not in the leaſt by me deſigned to be ſent abroad into the World. Your Lordſhip knew thoſe Obligations I lye un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to Your Lordſhip as my Kind and Noble Friend, and the Principle I go upon of ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to Authority; ſo that Your Lordſhip had me under a double tye, both of Gratitude and Obedience.</p>
            <p>I expect to bear a great many more hard Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and Invectives for this, though I have done no more then what I think was my bounden Duty to do: But thoſe things I have been ſo accuſtomed to hear, that I am now Clamour-proof; I had almoſt ſaid, that mine Ears are ſomewhat like a Traytors Conſcience, paſt all feeling. But (if I may have leave to expreſs my Real thoughts) I cannot but pitty Your Lordſhip and your Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Brethren, for Cauſing this Sermon to be Printed; becauſe hereby you have made it your own, and are Oblig'd in Honour to undertake for it, and to be my Defendants, if ever I ſhould be
<pb facs="tcp:93422:3"/> Threatned to be brought upon my Knees, or to ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> up my hand at the Bar for this, as I have been threatned formerly for things of the like Nature.</p>
            <p>And this I may think to be Security good e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough. But the miſchief is, that if ever tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Canicular days</hi> ſhould come again, Your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips will be in greater Jeopardy then my ſelf and then God help my Advocates as well
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Your Client.</p>
            <p>Let times be as it ſhall pleaſe God: It is, my Lord, your Honour that you are true to you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Duty; and it is my ſatisfaction, that I can in any thing Obey your Commands: And I do it with the more readineſs, becauſe it is obſerved how ready your Lordſhip and the reſt of the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es are to ſtand by the Intereſt of the Church, and upon all Occaſions publickly to Vindicate the Honour and Integrity of the Conformable and Loyal Clergy.</p>
            <p>That the God of peace, for whom you Judge, will Vouchſafe to preſerve you in your Great and Honourable Station, and ſupport your Courage, and Bleſs your Labours in the Miniſtration of Juſtice, and Eternally Reward your Faithfulneſs to the King, to the Church, and to the whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is, My Lord, the hearty Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt Obliged, and Obedient Servant, Edw. Pelling.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:93422:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Rom. 13. 2.</bibl>
               <q>Whoſoever therefore Reſiſteth the Power, Reſiſteth the Ordinance of God; and they that Reſiſt, ſhall receive to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Damnation.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>WHen the Chriſtian Religion began to be planted in the World, there were four very Evil Men, which in their turns Succeeded <hi>Auguſtus</hi> in the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire; <hi>Tiberius, Caligula, Claudius</hi> and <hi>Nero,</hi> (the latter of whom was the Man, that raiſed the firſt Perſecution againſt Chriſtians.) I do not know, but the Providence of God might order it thus, that all men might have the moſt early notices of their Duty to Princes, and that together with the true Faith, they might receive the neceſſary Doctrines of due Obedience and Subjection, to their Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Governours, whether good or bad. It was under <hi>Tiberius</hi> that Chriſt (the Great
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:93422:4"/> Biſhop of all our Souls) gave that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of rendering to <hi>Caeſar</hi> the things that were <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s, <hi>Matth.</hi> 22. 21. It was under <hi>Claudius,</hi> that St. <hi>Peter</hi> (the Great Apoſtle of the <hi>Jews</hi>) taught the diſperſed Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts, to ſubmit themſelves to every Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Man, for the Lords ſake; whether to the King as Supream, or unto Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours ſent by him, <hi>&amp;c. 1 Pet.</hi> 2. And (as 'tis generally conceived) it was under <hi>Nero,</hi> that St. <hi>Paul</hi> (the great Apoſtle of the
<hi>Gentiles</hi>) gave this ſo ſtrict a charge: <hi>Let every Soul be ſubject to the Higher Powers: Becauſe there is no Power but of God.</hi> Had not this thing been a prime part of the Chriſtian Religion, we cannot conceive why ſuch great care ſhould have been taken to inform the whole World of it, eſpecially in times which afforded not any common encouragements thereunto.</p>
            <p>Were it not a ſad Truth, that ſome will believe no more of the Scriptures, then what ſerves their preſent Turn, we might wonder how 'tis poſſible for a Chriſtian to be an Undutiful Subject. For, (as that great Chriſtian, and Divine; the Learned and Incomparable Dr.
<hi>Hammond</hi>) hath<note place="margin">Of Reſiſting the Lawful Magiſtrate.</note> rightly obſerved; In the New Teſtament,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:93422:4"/> eſpecially in the Epiſtles of the Apoſtles, (which were all Written in time of the Reign of Wicked, Heathen, Bloody Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Chriſtianity, and can refer to none but thoſe) there is no one Chriſtian Virtue, or Article of Faith more clearly delivered, more effectually inforced upon our Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings and Affections, to be acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the one, and ſubmitted to by the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then that of Obedience unto Kings.</p>
            <p>So that it is not either Ignorance that can excuſe, or any allowable principle of Chriſtianity that can encourage Reſiſtance; nor is it Zeal or Conſcience that doth it, though that has been pretended by ſome pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and ill natur'd Hypocrites; but 'tis ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an haughty and unmanageable Spirit, or an hankering after Spoyl, or an Aking Tooth after Government, or a Furious Rage for diſappointments, or Perſonal Spight, or hopes of Revenge, or the fear of Juſtice, or a Reſtleſs, Factious Humour, or direct Devilliſhneſs and Atheiſm under the Bonnet of Religion; ſome or all theſe things have ever been the true cauſes of thoſe Riots, which have been ſo Vexatious, ſo Fatal to Soveraign Powers: It being otherwiſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, that Men whoſe Conſciences are ſo
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:93422:5"/> Enlightned by Gods own Word; ſhould be ſo Blind, Wicked and Fool-hardy; as to Riſe up againſt their Prince, at the manifeſt hazard of the Greateſt and moſt Intolerable of all Evils: For that is the Rebels portion, if St. <hi>Paul</hi> may be credited, That they who reſiſt ſhall receive to themſelves Damnation.</p>
            <p>Yet I do not intend to declaim, though the World might well bear with me, and with all others, ſhould our mouths be full of the very Quinteſſence of bitterneſs; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially when we reflect upon that moſt Horrid and Execrable Murder, which was acted about this time upon the perſon of that Great Monarch and Martyr, of whom the World was not worthy, and perhaps will hardly ever ſee the like of him again. It would be a pittiful and woful thing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, ſhould not ſuch a ſuperlative piece of Villany ſtir at leaſt an honeſt mans Choler, and provoke him to ſpit ſome of it in the Rebels face. I hope things will not come to that paſs yet, but that we who then had not hands to reſcue a good Kings blood, may now be allowed the uſe of our Tongues to Revenge it, and I truſt in God our honeſt Poſterity will think ſo too.</p>
            <p>But I will charm my ſelf, as much as 'ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:93422:5"/> poſſible, and inſtead of breaking out into ſuch declamatory ſpeeches as this occaſion does juſtly require, I ſhall inſiſt upon the natural Senſe and Importance of my Text, and with what brevity I can, handle ſuch truths as may be eaſily diſcover'd by any Eye that is not blood-ſhot, or that doth not look aſquint upon our Government.</p>
            <p>In order hereunto we are to note, 1. That by reſiſtance here is meant in general all undu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful, diſobedient and contumacious beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, and in particular all open, forcible and violent Oppoſition. 2. That by the Power in my Text is meant, not only the Governours Authority, but the Governour himſelf, the Perſon of the Chief Magiſtrate who is veſted with the Supreme Authority. This is well to be obſerved, becauſe the Traytors of the late times proceeded upon a nice diſtinction between the Kings Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural and Politick capacity, cheating the World into a belief, that his Power was Lodged not in his Perſon, but in the Two Houſes of Parliament, and that 'twas not the Man in the Throne, but the Regal Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority which was virtually in the People, that was the thing ſacred. According to this ſophiſtical pretence, the King was againſt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:93422:6"/> himſelf; and ſuch as ſtood for him, were underſtood to Reſiſt his Power in defending his Perſon: So that in the upſhot 'twas his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty that was looked upon as the Traytor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the King, and they who deſtroy'd him, did not deſtroy their Soveraign, but did only cut off <hi>Charles Stuart:</hi> No, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious Juncto at
<hi>Weſtminſter</hi> were (in their own Language) the Kings moſt dutiful and moſt Loyal Subjects, even when they pull'd off his Crown, when one damned Faction held him by the Hair, and the other Godly Reprobates cut off his Head.</p>
            <p>After this rate was not the Apoſtle, a very Heterodox Malignant, an ill Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths-man, in not dividing the Kings Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority from his Perſon, but joyning both together? For he calls the Perſon of <hi>Nero,</hi> and other Princes <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream, or Higheſt Powers, <hi>v.</hi> 1. And by his following diſcourſe 'tis plain, that by the Power he doth mean the Perſon of the Magiſtrate that is in Chief, the perſon that preſideth over all, the perſon that is the Head of a Nation. For at the <hi>3d. 4th.</hi> and <hi>6th.</hi> Verſes he calls him expreſly the Ruler, the Miniſter of God, the man that beareth
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:93422:6"/> the Sword, the Revenger<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> pointing all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the perſon himſelf, that is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Tribute, to the perſon that is Gods Subſtitute and Deputy, to the perſon that is to praiſe them that do well, and Execute wrath upon evil-doers. Shall I take leave to give you a paraphraſe upon my Text? Why, you ſhall have it, not out of any ſingle Commentator that may be lookt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as an Arbitrary or Prerogative man, or onePopiſhly affected, but out of an honeſt Statute of this Realm, which makes St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Divinity to be Law too; the Act declares, <hi>That it is not lawful upon any pretence whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, to take Arms againſt the King, and that the Poſition of taking Arms by the Kings Authority againſt his Perſon, or againſt thoſe that are commiſſionated by him, is a Trayterous Poſition.</hi> Nay, there is another very ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant word yet, which commands every Subject to be an <hi>Abhorrer</hi> in this point, for faith the Law, it is a Traiterous poſition, to be <hi>Abhorr'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Text being thus opened, there are three grand Truths which it offers to every mans conſcience, and which cannot but ſtare in that Rebels face, whoſe conſcience
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s not ſeared with an hot Iron, though I
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:93422:7"/> think, there are few Rebels in the Land whoſe conſciences are not feared to a very Cruſt.</p>
            <p>1. That the Supreme Power, or the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority which is ſeated in the Kings Perſon, is the Ordinance of God himſelf.</p>
            <p>2. That becauſe the King is Gods own Miniſter, ordained Supreme by his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, no man muſt dare upon pain of Damnation, to uſe any violence againſt him.</p>
            <p>3. That conſidering what Princes were, who were the Supreme Powers in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> time, it is by no means lawful to reſiſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven wicked and Heathen Kings. And when theſe truths are a little laid open, Duty and Allegiance will further oblige us all to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the ſin of the Day.</p>
            <p>1. Firſt, That the Supreme Power, or the Authority which is ſeated in the Kings Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, is the Ordinance of God himſelf: Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever reſiſteth the Power, reſiſteth the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of God, ſaith the Apoſtle: And ſo this point paſſed all along uncontradicted through all Ages, till ſome counted it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> greater virtue to be Politicians, then to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Honeſt; I do not know one Chriſtian Write for 1600 years together, who ever denye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:93422:7"/> that the Power of the Civil Magiſtrate is of Divine Inſtitution; though
<hi>Jure Divino</hi> is now look't upon by ſome either, Fanciful or Ill Men, as a betraying of the Peoples Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties and Rights. And yet doth not the Apoſtle poſitively tell us, that there is no power but of God? <hi>v.</hi> 1. And to prevent a miſtake; for fear we ſhould interpret this of Gods Permiſſion only, he tells us in the next breath, that the Powers that be, are Ordained of God: And that is much more than Permiſſion. He hath permitted Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſors and Uſurpers, <hi>Bradſhaws, Cromwels,</hi> and ſuch like Excrements of Nature: But he never appointed, or Ordained them as he doth every Lawful Prince. No; the Commiſſion, the Authority of a Lawful Prince is from above; ſo that he is, <hi>Homo à Deo ſecundus, &amp; quicquid eſt à Deo conſecutus, &amp; Solo Deo minor, as Tertullian</hi> (and all Chriſtians then) believed; a Man next un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, holding all his Regalities of God, Inferior to God alone. And indeed how could St. <hi>Paul</hi> call Kings, the Miniſters of God (as he doth Thrice for failing, in 2. Verſes of this Chapter) were not the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Kings by Divine Right, or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation? All the Apoſtles expreſſions are
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:93422:8"/> ſo clear, ſo ſignificant, ſo full on the Kings behalf, that I ſhould be loth to ſee the Tythe of ſo much, for a Chair-man in a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, or for a Pariſh Pope, or for a Lay-Elder: Nay, did the Scriptures ſpeak but the Hundredth part ſo much on their ſide, what a Noiſe, and Duſt ſhould we have about <hi>Jus Divinum</hi> then?</p>
            <p>Many men do not underſtand what we mean, when we ſay that this or that thing is <hi>de Jure Divino:</hi> many dangerous and miſchievous Errors have been occaſioned through mens Ignorance in this particular. Therefore for the right underſtanding of this matter, we muſt know that a thing may be ſaid to be <hi>Jure Divino</hi> either in a ſtrict, or in a larger ſenſe.</p>
            <p>1. In a ſtrict ſenſe, when we find it in the Word of God to be Ordained by ſuch an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Command, as that the neglect there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of becometh Sinful. Now when we ſpeak of the Divine Right of Monarchy, we do not mean that God did inſtitute it ſo, by his Expreſs Command, as if all other Forms of Government were abſolutely Unlawful, or as if it were unlawful for a Monarch to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract his Power, or ſet Limits to himſelf in the Uſe and Exerciſe of his Power. No; Princes
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:93422:8"/> may tye up their own hands themſelves, tho it be not Lawful for their Subjects to force Manacles upon them: Kings may Abate much of their Greatneſs, if they will: 'tis law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for them to do it <hi>pro re natâ,</hi> though it be Impolitick and Unſafe for them and for their Subjects too, to do ſo at every Turn. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there is no ground for thoſe Odious and Baſe Reflections which of late have been made upon the honeſt Clergy of this<note place="margin">See Mr. <hi>Hunts</hi> Poſt-ſcript,</note> Church, as if they were Friends to Arbitrary Power, and Tyranny, and the like, for aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerting the Kings Power to be of Divine O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal. Theſe are Lewd and Unjuſt cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures: But ſo it is, that if any dirt can be raked out of the Kennel, the Clergy ſhall be ſure to have ſtore of it thrown upon their Faces.</p>
            <p>2. A thing is ſaid to be <hi>Jure divino</hi> in a Larger ſenſe.</p>
            <p>1. When the Scriptures declare it to be Ordained of God, though we cannot ſhew the Original Command, or the preciſe time of its Inſtitution:</p>
            <p>2. Or Secondly, when we have ſtrong and highly Probable Reaſons to believe it (tho there were no Declarations on that behalf.)</p>
            <p>1. Partly from the great Congruity of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:93422:9"/> the thing, by reaſon whereof it ſeems to be Morally and Humanely Neceſſary;</p>
            <p>2. Partly from ſeveral Inſinuations in Scripture, which render the thing very Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble:</p>
            <p>3. And partly from the General practice of all Mankind, who would not (as we can ſuppoſe) have conſented in the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Obſervation of the thing, had not God given ſome Law or other for it in the beginning.</p>
            <p>Now then to apply this matter to our preſent purpoſe;</p>
            <p>1. Thoſe places of Scripture which I have alleadged already, do abundantly declare, that the King hath his Power and Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty from God. And this is enough to ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie any Sober Man, who hath any Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence for the Scripture, that Kingly Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was inſtituted by God (as the beſt of Governments) though we could not Trace the Inſtitution of it clearly to the Fountain Head. For in a matter of ſo Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote Antiquity, it is not eaſie to Salve all doubts, or to take away all occaſion of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil from every Witty and Inquiſitive So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſter. As long as God hath declared, that Kings Reign by Him, 'tis Reaſonable
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:93422:9"/> for us to reſt in that, ſhould we not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to anſwer that Impudent Queſtion, which hath been ask't us of Late, <hi>Where is the Charter for Kings?</hi> 'Tis in the Bible, we ſee: And that muſt ſatisfie me, though I could not tell when, or where, or how it was firſt Signed.</p>
            <p>2. But then, <hi>2ly.</hi> It hath been found by the certain Experience of all Ages, that Monarchy is ſo Excellent, ſo Incomparably beyond all other Forms, ſo uſeful for the Ends of Government, and in many Caſes ſo extreamly neceſſary for the publick Good; that 'tis reaſonable to conclude from the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Congruity of the thing, that Kings were Ordained of God; becauſe 'tis Reaſonable to believe, that in the Beginning God did Order every thing for the Beſt, did Inſtitute that Government which is moſt for the good of Prince and People too, and made the World for us all not to plague one another, but to be Happy in, as long as we ſtay in it.</p>
            <p>3. Beſides this, Thirdly, the Scripture gives us ſuch plain, ſuch pregnant Inſinuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons touching matter of Fact in this point, as do abundantly juſtifie the <hi>Jus Divinum</hi> of Regal power, to be no Idle, no Groundleſs Notion. Go to the Creation, and you will
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:93422:10"/> find, that God Inveſted <hi>Adam</hi> with a pleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of power over all Creatures, over his very Wife, and by conſequence over all her Iſſue.</p>
            <p>This the Apoſtle calleth, a Law 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14 34. and as the Law which God gave to all his Works was to hold and laſt to the World's End; ſo this Law touching Superiority and Subjection under one perſon, ſeems as if it was intended to continue, and to deſcend from Father to Son by Right of Primogeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. And this I take to have been the True Reaſon of that deadly Quarrel which <hi>Cain</hi> had againſt his Righteous Brother. When he ſaw that God had a particular re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to <hi>Abel</hi> and his Offerings, he was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid leſt <hi>Abel</hi> ſhould go away with the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal power; and ſo he contrived to be rid of him, not ſo much out of Envy, as out of Ambition, for fear he ſhould loſe his Birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right. To quiet his mind as to that, God told him, that <hi>if he did well, he ſhould have the Excellence;</hi> that <hi>his Brothers deſire ſhould be ſubject unto him, and that he ſhould Rule over him</hi> (which was the very Form of words, whereby the Protoplaſt was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted with Authority over his Wife.) And St. <hi>Chryſoſton</hi> Rightly obſerves, that though
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:93422:10"/> God was diſpleaſed with <hi>Cain,</hi> yet he did not preſently deprive him of his juſt Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and power, but allowed him ſtill <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the Priviledges of Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mogeniture.</p>
            <p>Thus it was in the Times before the<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Primo geniti per Patris aut Mortem aut abſentiam, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternam quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dammòdo au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoritatem in fratres habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant: Sed hoc jus Peccato a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitti poterat. Gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t. Annot. ad Gen.</hi> 4.
7.</note> Flood: Right of Dominion was ordered by God to Deſcend by Inheritance; and ſo it did actually deſcend, where God himſelf did not cut off that Right which he had giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, for ſome Important Reaſons.</p>
            <p>In the times after the Flood, Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment went in the ſame Channel. So <hi>Reuben</hi> was called the <hi>Excellency of Dignity, and the Excellency of Power,</hi> becauſe he was the
<hi>Firſt-Born.</hi> And <hi>Eſau</hi> ſhould have been a Lord and Prince over
<hi>Jacob,</hi> had he not Sold his Birth-right; and becauſe he Sold it, he is called a
<hi>Prophane perſon</hi> for Sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling that which was not his <hi>own;</hi> it was a
<hi>Sacred</hi> thing, a Donative from God; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was Curſed for Selling it for a meſs of Pottage.</p>
            <p>But here we muſt note, that when Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies increaſed, ſo that they were forced to part into ſeveral Colonies for want of Room; by the grant and Donation of the Father each Son became a diſtinct Prince,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:93422:11"/> having a diſtinct Empire over his own Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily; and by ſuch Diviſions and Subdiviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons it came to paſs, that ſo many Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies were ſet up in the World in a ſhort time. Hence it was that <hi>Nimrod</hi> had a Kingdom of his own: And the Scripture calls him a <hi>Mighty Hunter,</hi> not becauſe he was a <hi>Monarch,</hi> but becauſe he was a Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent <hi>Encroacher;</hi> becauſe not content with his own Empire, he Invaded the Rights and Royalties of others, who were Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigns within their Territories, as well as himſelf. Hence it is too, that upon that<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee Mr.
<hi>Med<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iatrib. in <hi>Gen.</hi> 10.</note> Orderly diſperſion of the Sons of <hi>Noah,</hi> the whole Earth was by degrees divided into a great many Kingdoms; ſo that of <hi>Noah,</hi> Iſſue there were I know not how many Kings in a ſhort time. They were divided <hi>after their Tongues, after their Families, after their Generations, in their ſeveral Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Countries,</hi> as the Scripture often tells us,
<hi>Gen.</hi> 10. <hi>Thus</hi> all the Monarchies in the World were Founded; not by <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples chuſing</hi> their Leaders and Governours, but by <hi>Princes going out</hi> with their Reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ive Families, and uſing a Soveraign Power over them, purſuant to Gods Inſtitution and Ordinance, that the <hi>Head and Chief</hi> of a
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:93422:11"/> Family ſhould have Dominion and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity over the reſt.</p>
            <p>Hence alſo it was, that we read of Twelve Princes out of the Loins of <hi>Iſhmael;</hi> and of ſeveral Dukes which Sprang out of the Loins of <hi>Eſau.</hi> For every Head of a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct Great Family was by the Divine ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment a King in his Nation; and his Kingdom was of greater or leſs Extent, as his Family was more or leſs Numerous. And hence, laſtly, it was, that we Read of many Kingdoms in one Country (as in <hi>Canaan,</hi> for Inſtance) becauſe their Territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries were according to their Numbers: So that Antiently Principalities were but ſmall, till by the Union of many Great Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies (either by Conqueſt and Force, or by Voluntary Submiſſion) Great Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies and Empires came to be Erected.</p>
            <p>4. And this brings me to the laſt Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, to prove the <hi>Jus Divinum</hi> of Kingly Power; <hi>viz.</hi> The Univerſal practice of all Nations. For nothing can be more plain, than that Kingly Government was the only Government (we know of) in the whole World for ſome Thouſand Years together. The <hi>Greeks</hi> were under Monarchs all along, till ſuch a Frenzy poſſeſt ſome of them, as
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:93422:12"/> hath poſſeſt ſome Bedlams among us, to change their Old Government for a New nothing: But their Madneſs did coſt them very dear in the End; they were Undone and Ruin'd by it, as we ſhould ſoon be by our Innovations. In the moſt Antient Times there was no ſuch thing as an Ariſtocratick or Democratick State: And the Reaſon why the <hi>Jews</hi> would needs have a King (though thy were under a Theocracy) was, becauſe they would not be Singular; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they would have a King to Judg them, as all the Nations (all other Nations) had, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8. 5. Now, <hi>Lex currit cum praxi;</hi> the Univerſal Practice of the World is a ſtrong argument to prove, that there was ſome Antecedent Law, which (as they ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed) did lay ſome Obligation upon them; becauſe people are not very forward to fall under Government of themſelves (ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them to be in a State of Liberty:) Nor is it conceivable that all Men in the World ſhould be of one mind, or that one Form of Government ſhould pleaſe all; eſpecially that Government which is in the hands of one Man: We may as ſoon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that all parts of the World did fall aſleep at once, and then all on a ſudden
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:93422:12"/> did awake into ſo many Formed and Setled Monarchies.</p>
            <p>By this time, I hope, it doth appear, that there are ſtronger Reaſons for the Doctrine of the <hi>Jus Divinum</hi> of Regal Power, then that it ſhould be lookt upon as a State Hereſie of a Modern date, and of dangerous Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence. The ſutableneſs thereof to Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane neceſſities, the Concurrence of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-hiſtory, which doth plainly Inſinuate the Inſtitution, the Original, the Uſage of Monarchical Dominion, together with the Suffrages of all Mankind, who for a long Tract of Ages ſubmitted unto it, as if it were Entailed upon them from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: All this, I ſay, doth clearly argue as well the Truth as the Reaſon of this Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, that the Kings power is Gods Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</p>
            <p>Which ſerves alſo to baffle thoſe Wild and groundleſs conceits which our Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lican Spirits are ſo very fond of; that there was once a State of Nature, wherein all Mankind were Free, under their own Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and at their own choice, whether they would have Government or no Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and whether they would have this Form or another. Theſe and the like are
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:93422:13"/> no other then the Lewd and Idle conceits of Factious Brains: For there never was ſuch a State of Nature, but in the Imagination of ſuch Brainſick Men who have fancied a World in the Moon: Whoſoever has come out of the Womb hath been Born un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Government; nay, under Kingly Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, till Rebellion, or Faction, or the Love of Novelty altered the Natural and Regular courſe of affairs. I do not blame <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> and other Old Infidels, for not hitting well upon the True Original of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, conſidering they were not well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the Scriptures, but ſpake for the moſt part by gueſs.</p>
            <p>But I wonder at the confidence of <hi>Hobbs</hi> and other ſuch Modern Politicians (though in truth even they are for the moſt part Infidels too) for talking ſo idly and unphiloſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally, as that Kings have their Authority by Compact and Covenant, and the pleaſure of the people; ſo that they may Crown them, or Un-king them, as they think fit; Doctrines, which coſt King <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>1ſt,</hi> of Bleſſed Memory, no leſs then his Crown and his Head too. Whereas! for many A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges after the Creation, Regal Authority de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended by Inheritance; and as Nature gave
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:93422:13"/> a Man the Father-hood, ſo the Authority which went along with it, was Gods Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>native; people did no more chuſe their Kings, then Children do chuſe their Fathers. As for Common-wealths, and Ariſtocracies and Elective States, the World formerly was unacquainted with them; nay the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Names of them were unknown: No, they are only ſo many Uſurpations, Degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and Baſtard ſorts of Government: The Monarchical Form as it is far the beſt, ſo
'tis incomparably the Oldeſt, and of Gods own Inſtitution: The reſt are but Upſtarts and Muſhrooms of yeſterday in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; and I think, 'tis nothing but the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities of ſome few places in the World, that makes them either Tolerable or Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</p>
            <p>2. I have done with the firſt point, That the Kings Power is Gods Ordinance, and it brings me to the <hi>2d,</hi> That becauſe the King is Gods own Miniſter, Ordained Supreme by his Commiſſion, no man muſt dare up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on pain of Damnation, to uſe any Violence againſt him,
<hi>they that Reſiſt, ſhall receive to themſelves Damnation.</hi> For, if God will Judg the Open and the Secret Actions of men according to the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:93422:14"/> every man according to his Works, what leſs can the bold <hi>Rebe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> expect, then the <hi>Severities</hi> of Judgment, that preſumes in ſpight of all the Out-cries of Conſcience, to act that which is ſo contrary to the <hi>Ends</hi> of Government; ſo <hi>Reproachful</hi> to the Goſpel, ſo repugnant to the <hi>Spirit</hi> of its <hi>Author</hi> and its <hi>Laws?</hi> Did not Chriſt ſuffer for us, leaving us an example that we ſhould follow his ſteps? 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2 21. Did not his Peaceable and Submiſſive deportment all along Teach us, that all Undutifulneſs and Violence muſt be utterly forborn? Did he not pay <hi>Caeſar</hi> his Tribute with a plain com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand that every Diſciple of his ſhould pay him his due? Did he not Rebuke thoſe, who would have called for Fire upon the Heads of the <hi>Samaritanes?</hi> Did he not recommend to us the Practice of his Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, Meekneſs, and Patience under the Croſs? Was he not angry with
<hi>Peter</hi> for drawing his Sword upon the Chief-Prieſts Servants? Did he not own
<hi>Pilates</hi> Power to have been from above? Did he not ſubmit to it, when he had at his Command 12 Legions of Angels? Did not every Inſtance of his Life ſhew us, that 'tis better far to Die, then to Reſiſt? Why, <hi>this</hi> was <hi>Chriſts</hi> Religion;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:93422:14"/> and this is Chriſtianity, that we ſhould be <hi>Conformed to the Image of Chriſt, Rom.</hi> 8. 29. That's the Subſtance, the Power, the Life of Chriſtianity: That's the buſineſs and Office of every Chriſtian: And though Men pleaſe themſelves with other popular Names, and call themſelves the only <hi>true Catholicks</hi> on the one hand, and the only <hi>true Proteſtants</hi> on the other; yet as long as they are Diſloyal on either hand; as long as they are <hi>Gun-powder</hi> Catholicks, or <hi>Cut-throat</hi> True Proteſtants; as long as they ſhoot at Government either with <hi>Bulls,</hi> or with <hi>Ordinances,</hi> as long as <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſults</hi> or <hi>Covenants</hi> are in Faſhion with them, and the King cannot be ſafe for them neither in the Field, nor at Home; as long as they Act after this Deviliſh rate, they do but abuſe themſelves into a State of Damnation, for all their fine Names; they ought not to be called <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> or if they will wrongfully Uſurp <hi>that</hi> Name too, there are as good Chriſtians as they with <hi>Korah</hi> and <hi>Judas;</hi> and I had rather be a meer Philoſopher, or an honeſt Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, then <hi>ſuch</hi> a Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>And doth not the Goſpel ſtrictly Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand us, not to Strive, not to Reſiſt Evil,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:93422:15"/> but to be Charitable, Patient and Peaceable, to obey Magiſtrates, to Honour the King, to Submit to our Rulers, to be Quiet, to do our own Buſineſs, and to be ſubject for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſake? many Commands more we meet with up and down which hallow the Authority, and immure the Throne of the Chief Magiſtrate. And doth not my Text award Damnation to every Rebel? Why, one would think, that ſuch Men did uſe ſome <hi>other</hi> Goſpel, ſince they have no be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit by <hi>this,</hi> nothing but <hi>Damnation</hi> by the Goſpel of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Certainly they have a Goſpel by <hi>themſelves; Evangelium Armatum,</hi> a Goſpel that is covered in Armour and dipt in Blood: For by <hi>ours,</hi> there is no Salvation for them, without ſuch a Stinging Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance as St. <hi>Paul</hi> deſcribes in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 11.</p>
            <p>But I ſhall not need to proceed further upon the proof of this Matter, becauſe the clearing of the <hi>3d.</hi> Point will ſerve <hi>à Fortiori</hi> to confirm this. Only give me leave, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I come to it, to note how the Apoſtle in my Text doth Limit Non-Reſiſtance. He forbids Reſiſtance againſt the Governour in <hi>Chief,</hi> againſt him that is the
<hi>Fountain</hi> of all Authority in the Kingdom. Let every <hi>Soul be Subject</hi> (but) to the
<hi>Higher</hi> (that
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:93422:15"/> is, to the <hi>bigheſt,</hi> or Supreme) Powers. And ſo in my Text, he that Reſiſteth the Power, meaning the ſame Power, that is the Power, the Authority, the Magiſtrate that is over <hi>all:</hi> Whether it be King as <hi>Supreme,</hi> ſaith St.
<hi>Peter,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 13. Supremacy was in the <hi>Crown</hi> in thoſe days; there the High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Power is Lodged, and <hi>that</hi> is the Power we muſt be ſubject unto for
<hi>Conſcience ſake.</hi> Other Uſurping and pretending Powers Men may be forced ſometimes to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject unto upon pain of <hi>Plunder</hi> and <hi>Sequeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration;</hi> but the
<hi>Supreme</hi> Power, the <hi>King</hi> is he, whom we muſt not Reſiſt upon pain of
<hi>Damnation.</hi> There is in every King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom the Supreme, and a Subordinate Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy. So St.
<hi>Peter</hi> doth diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>King that is Supreme, and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours that are ſent by Him.</hi> The King is <hi>Gods</hi> Repreſentative, other Subordinate Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours are the King's: And as long as thoſe Governours Act Regularly, and according to their Commiſſion, they are to be obeyed too. But I will ſpeak a blunt Truth, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever be the Iſſue of it, ſhould our Nation be ſo unhappy again as it was in 42. when Inferior (or rather, Uſurping) Powers for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſook their <hi>Allegiance, Levyed a War, Raiſed
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:93422:16"/> Arms, Iſſued out Commiſſions, and turned the points of their Swords againſt the Supreme (and only Lawful) Power,</hi> it would be not only allowable and Lawful, but
'twould be the Peoples Duty, and in point of Conſcience a neceſſary Duty to Reſiſt ſuch Power even unto Blood, though Ten Thouſand Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Parliament (were there ſo many) ſhould pretend to it.</p>
            <p>Perhaps I might have ſpared that Hint in this Age, when our former ſufferings on each ſide, ſhould be enough (one would think) to make all Men Wiſe, and for their Intereſt (if not for Conſcience) ſake to be Dutiful for the Future. But I could not baulk it well, without baulking ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in my Text which forbiddeth all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance againſt the
<hi>Supreme</hi> or <hi>Soveraign</hi> Power.</p>
            <p>3. That Power is priviledg'd from all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, though the King ſhould happen to be a Wicked, or an Heathen Prince; which is the <hi>3d.</hi> and laſt point, and it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded from the Conſideration of what thoſe Princes were, when the Apoſtles were plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſtianity: For when St. <hi>Peter</hi> wrote his Firſt Epiſtle, wherein he Charged Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans to Submit to the King as Supreme, and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:93422:16"/> unto Governours, his Miniſters of State, Chriſtians were ſo hardly dealt with, that they were forced to Flee up and down into places where they could beſt ſhift, into
<hi>Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, Galatia,</hi> and divers Provinces more, as we find at the beginning of that Epiſtle. And <hi>Claudius</hi> himſelf, who probably was Emperour at that Time, was a Man of a Cruel diſpoſition, Zealous for Heatheniſh Idolatry, Severe to all of a Foreign Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, ſo that he would not ſuffer the <hi>Jews</hi> to meet together (ſaith <hi>Dio;</hi>) and at laſt he Expel'd the whole Body of <hi>Jews</hi> out of <hi>Rome</hi> (Believers, and Unbelievers too,) and that upon Chriſts account, ſaith <hi>Suetonius,</hi> ſuch was the Emperour, and ſuch were his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, that they would not allow Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans neither the exerciſe of their Religion, nor the Liberty of their Native Countries, nor the protection of their own Houſes; and yet, both <hi>Claudius</hi> and his Deputies muſt be ſubmitted unto. After
<hi>Claudius</hi> imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately came <hi>Nero</hi> to be Emperour: A man called a Lyon by St.
<hi>Paul</hi> himſelf, becauſe he was of a Savage and ferine mind, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially after he had got a taſt of Blood (that I may ſave <hi>Seneca's</hi> credit in his Book <hi>de Clementià:</hi>) A Man that kill'd his Tutor af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:93422:17"/> all his Courtſhip of him; that diſpatche his Wife and Ript open the Bowels of his Own Mother. A man that had a ſpight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt every thing that was Good (ſaith
<hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian,</hi>) and that ſome Chriſtians took to have been the <hi>Antichriſt</hi> ſpoken of. For he was the Man that rais'd the firſt of the Ten Famous and General Perſecutions, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted puniſhments upon Chriſtians, ſaith <hi>Suetonius;</hi> put them to the moſt exquiſite Torments, ſaith <hi>Cornelius Tacitus.</hi> For he Crucified ſome, and others he Burned. And as before, he ſet Fire on <hi>Rome,</hi> that he might pleaſe himſelf with the Reſemblance of the Burning of <hi>Troy,</hi> ſo after that he burnt Chriſtians in huge Heaps and Piles, that the light of the Fires might direct Paſſengers in dark Nights (ſaith the <hi>Hiſtorian:</hi>) and not content with all this Cruelty, many Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans he dreſt up in the Skins of Wild Beaſts, that they might be Torn in pieces by Dogs, as the ſame <hi>Tacitus</hi> Relates further. It was in the Reign of this Monſter of Men, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> liv'd, by this Token, that he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that Apoſtle himſelf to be Beheaded; and it was in the <hi>2d.</hi> Year of <hi>Nero</hi> (as 'tis probably conjectur'd by
<hi>Baronius</hi> out of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigen</hi>) that St. <hi>Paul</hi> wrote this Epiſtle to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:93422:17"/> the Chriſtians in and about the Imperial Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: And though St. <hi>Paul</hi> knew enough of the Man already, and the Spirit of God foreſaw a great deal more, yet you ſee what was written touching Subjection even to him (who was a ſhame to all Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces) even this,
<hi>Let every Soul be ſubject to the Higheſt Powers; for there is no Power but of God: The Powers that be, are Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained of God: Whoſoever therefore Reſiſteth the Power, Reſiſteth the Ordinance of God, and they that Reſiſt ſhall receive to themſelves Damnation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againſt this that hath been ſpoken there is one popular objection which I muſt take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of, and it is this: That where a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom hath adopted the True Religion, ſo that it is Eſtabliſht by publick Authority (as God be Bleſſed it is in this Kingdom) and the Laws of the Country are on its ſide, there Reſiſtance is not unlawful, if a Prince doth indeavour the Deſtruction or Alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the True Faith.</p>
            <p>In anſwer hereunto theſe things in ſhort are to be conſidered.</p>
            <p>1. Firſt that the true Religion was Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſht in the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> State by the Municipal Laws of that Nation, and that by the Authority
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:93422:18"/> of God himſelf and yet, though ſeveral Kings did attempt the introduction of Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, nay did actually introduce it, the <hi>Jews</hi> Reſiſted not nevertheleſs, and if they had Reſiſted, ſuch Reſiſtance had been ſinful notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>2. It is very hard and unjuſt, that Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces Favours ſhould be made uſe of againſt themſelves, that their Prerogatives ſhould be prejudiced for their having received the Faith, and for the Kindneſſes they have ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Church of Chriſt. Becauſe
<hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi> was a Zealous Protector of the true Religion, it would have been highly Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable, ſhould this have redounded to the Violation of the Imperial Dignity of his Son
<hi>Conſtantius.</hi> The Primitive Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans had the Laws of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> on their ſide: And yet they did not think Reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance Lawful, though the Son was an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to that Faith, of which the Father was the Defender.</p>
            <p>3. No Laws ought to be pleaded beyond their plain Deſign and Meaning. Now the intent of our Laws is to ſecure our Religion againſt <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> and <hi>Hereticks;</hi> but not to Arm Subjects againſt their Prince. For the ſame Laws which are the Stabiliment
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:93422:18"/> of the Church, do manifeſtly and Roundly declare all Reſiſtance to be unlawful and Treaſonable, and do Agnize the power of the Sword to be in the King, and in the King only: So that <hi>no Law</hi> is on our ſide as to matter of <hi>Reſiſtance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4. Should our Laws be ſo bad, as to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of Reſiſtance in <hi>ſome</hi> Caſes, yet this could be no Bar againſt the Laws of God which forbid Reſiſtance in <hi>all</hi> Caſes. For it is not in the power of men to give us leave to Sin; nor can any Humane Authority give us the liberty whether we will obey the Commands of Chriſt or no. I may not in any wiſe Hurt my Prince, had I his own leave for it, <hi>becauſe the King of Kings hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded me under pain of his high diſpleaſure to do the Contrary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>5. Nay I will be bold to ſay, in the laſt place that ſuppoſing Law-givers ſhould be ſo Impolitick as under pain of Death to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire,</hi> and by a Formed Law to
<hi>command</hi> us to Reſiſt the Soveraign power, it ought not in any wiſe to be done however. For it is a ſtanding Rule in Chriſtianity, that Authority is not to be obeyed in things that are Unlawful, now Reſiſtance is ſimply and in its own Nature Sinful; and all
<hi>Caſuiſts</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:93422:19"/> will tell us, that <hi>rei illicitae nulla eſt obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio,</hi> an Unlawful Command cannot bind, unleſs it be to Sufferings; ſuch a command would be Null and Void of it ſelf; the matter of a Law ſomtimes taking off its Obligation, when 'tis contrary to the Laws of God and Nature; and ſuch would a Law for Reſiſtance be, ſhould the Authority of the whole Kingdom conſent to it.</p>
            <p>I have done now with the Conſideration of my Text, and come at length to the day: but am at a great loſs, how or where to begin, or in what Language to expreſs my Senſe of that Superlative Villany Acted at this time; which hath ſtain'd the Conſciences of Rebels with Blood, which hath dyed the Faces of all Chriſtians with ſhame, which hath brought upon all Engliſh Men a per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>petual Reproach, which was an aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to all Nations, a blow to all Thrones, a wound to the hearts of all Princes, a Con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tumely to Heaven, and ſuch an horrid Af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>front to the great God, that I am afraid, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever Judgments and Plagues we have la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured under ſince, or do labour under ſtill, have fallen upon our Heads as the Returns of that Cry,
<hi>with which the Sacred Blood of the Lords Anointed, his late Majeſty, went up to</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:93422:19"/> Heaven. I pray God our Land may be once throughly cleanſed from the Guilt of it. The Blood of Chriſt can, and nothing but Chriſts own blood can purge us. And I am of the opinion, that if the blood of any Prince or Martyr could be ſo valuable and precious, as never to be atoned for in this World, it would be that <hi>Royal,</hi> that <hi>Sacred,</hi> that
<hi>Innocent</hi> blood, which was ſo barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly ſhed upon the Earth, as at this time.</p>
            <p>As often as I caſt my thoughts upon the conſideration of this moſt Horrid Fact, I cannot but think on thoſe Memorable words of <hi>David,</hi> to the <hi>Amalekite</hi> upon the death of
<hi>Saul.</hi> Part of the whole Story we have in 2 <hi>Sam. 1. Saul</hi> indeed had killed himſelf with his own Sword, at leaſt, had given him<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelf his Deaths-wound. This
<hi>Amalekite</hi> took off the Crown from his Head, and the Bracelet from his Arm, and brought both unto <hi>David,</hi> pretending that <hi>he</hi> had ſlain <hi>Saul.</hi> Very probable it is, that he hoped for ſome good reward at <hi>Davids</hi> Hands (which has ſomtimes been the Traitors For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune;) and he was the firſt I read of, that counted King killing a
<hi>Meritorious</hi> Act: But inſtead of reaping his expected <hi>Boo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty</hi> he obtain'd not ſo much as a <hi>Para<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:93422:20"/> but receiv'd his Final and deſerved Doom. <hi>David</hi> ſtood amaz'd and aſtoniſht at the Villany <hi>How waſt thou not afraid</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſtretch forth thine hand, to deſtroy the Lords Anointed? 2 Sam.</hi> 1. 14. It was a
<hi>Formidable</hi> and <hi>dreadful</hi> Crime in <hi>Davids</hi> account: And yet there are ſome Circum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtances in that Story, which thoſe Accurſed Regicides in 48 would have uſed to have <hi>Juſtified</hi> their Fact, had the Caſe then been Parallel. For firſt, as for
<hi>this</hi> Villain; he was no <hi>Jew,</hi> nor, (by what we find of him) any ſworn Subject of
<hi>Sauls: I am,</hi> ſaith he<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>the Son of a Stranger,</hi> an <hi>Amalekite, v. 13.
2ly,</hi> as for <hi>Saul</hi> Himſelf, he was a Man that had been Rejected of God for his Diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience: A Man full of ſpight and cauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Revenge; a Man ſo wicked, as that he conſulted with the Devil, when he applyed himſelf to the Witch at <hi>End or?</hi> And yet for all this you ſee, <hi>David</hi> called him the <hi>Lords Anointed.</hi> Beſides, he was a Man ſo implacably ſet againſt <hi>David</hi> in particular, that he purſued him like a
<hi>Partridge</hi> upon the Mountains, and would gladly have been at any Labour or Goſt to have made him away<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> notwithſtanding all his Honourable Atchieve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ments even for <hi>Sauls</hi> ſake. Nevertheleſs
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:93422:20"/> though <hi>David</hi> was ſure to<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Succeed him
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in the Throne, and ſo was little Concern'd (in compariſon) in point of <hi>Intereſt,</hi> either to have ſpared him <hi>himſelf,</hi> or to have Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged his Blood being ſhed by <hi>another;</hi> yet be did not only himſelf let him go, when he had him in his Power (nay, his Heart ſmote him, when he only cut off the skirt of his Mantle,) but as ſoon as this <hi>Amalekite</hi> had own'd that he had ſlain him, he ſtraight ordered him to be Executed, with theſe upbraiding and wrath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful words<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>How waſt thou not afraid to ſtretch forth thine hand to deſtroy the Lords Anointed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And what a fearful ſin was that then<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which was at this time acted? 1. By per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, that were the Kings Natural and Born<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Subjects, Members and Children, as it were, of his Family; ſuch as he had a natural intereſt in, ſuch as lay under all thoſe obligations, which God and Nature ever laid upon Men, to Obey and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, to Revere and Love the great and common Father of the Country, who was no more accountable to his Subjects, then Parents are puniſhable by thoſe of their own Houſe-hold. So that the ſin of this day was not only
<hi>Murder,</hi> but <hi>Parricide</hi> too. A crime, which the very Heathens of old did
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:93422:21"/> not dream, that it could enter into any Mans thought to meditate, therefore nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Numa</hi> nor <hi>Solon</hi> made any Laws againſt it. But when <hi>Hoſtius</hi> and <hi>Malleolus</hi> had once taken the heart to kill their Parents, then it was provided, that all ſuch <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> Wretches (or <hi>Brutes</hi> rather) ſhould be <hi>burnt alive, or drowned in the Sea with Dogs, or be caſt to the wild Beaſts, or be tumbled headlong from the top of ſome tugged Precipice.</hi> And yet, Secondly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides theſe <hi>natural</hi> obligations, there were <hi>voluntary</hi> and <hi>Adventitious</hi> ones, which thoſe perſons laid <hi>themſelves</hi> under; the moſt ſacred tyes in the World, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore called the Oaths of <hi>God;</hi> I mean the Oaths of <hi>Allegiance and Supremacy,</hi> which no Man can break, but muſt be in danger of Hell-Fire. We thought once, that the deviliſh ſtratagem of diſpenſing with Oaths, and of Abſolving Men from their Allegiance, had been the work of the
<hi>Pope</hi> only; to prove whom to be Antichriſt, one of the beſt Arguments is this, that
<hi>he exalteth himſelf above all that is called God,</hi> that is, <hi>above the Kings of the Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:93422:21"/>But it ſeems, ſome who were great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending Enemies to Popery<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> could Diſpenſe with <hi>themſelves,</hi> and Abſolve <hi>themſelves,</hi> and that at a
<hi>cheaper</hi> rate too: So that in ſpight of Honour, Nature, Religion, and all the moſt ſtrict and inviolable bands upon the Conſcience, they took the unparallel'd boldneſs, not only to invade his Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, to diveſt him of his Regalities, and to number him among Traytors (even be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath <hi>themſelves,</hi> the very <hi>Worſt</hi> and <hi>Rank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt</hi> of all Traytors,) but after they had cut off his <hi>Locks,</hi> and taken off his <hi>Crown,</hi> they proceeded yet further, even to ſtretch forth their hands to <hi>deſtroy the Life</hi> of Gods Anointed, than which nothing under Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven could be ſecured with a more ſacred Fence.</p>
            <p>And yet behold a greater than <hi>Saul</hi> was here: A Prince, for Intellectual and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral virtues, for Natural and Acquired ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhments, for Wiſdom, Eloquence, and all kinds of Literature, for his ſincere Piety, for his Chriſtian and well-govern'd Zeal; for his Exemplary Temperance, for his Unſpotted Chaſtity, for his Invincible Patience, for his Inexhauſtible Clemency, for the Tenderneſs and Compaſſions of his
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:93422:22"/> Heart, for his moſt Condeſcending and Gracious Spirit, for his Love to God, to his People, to the Church, for his Courage, Conſtancy, and ſingular Chriſtian Charity even to his Enemies, and to his laſt breath; for all neceſſary and admirable Endowments, becoming a Man, a Chriſtian, a King, a Martyr, he was a Prince by the confeſſion of the World ſo Heroick, Singular, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable, that even a Romiſh Prieſt gave this character of him, that he was the greateſt of Men and of Kings, <hi>niſi quod Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticus,</hi> only he was an<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Heretick (in their account,) that is, in truth, he prov'd a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender, Reign'd a Confeſſor, Liv'd a Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and Dyed a Martyr for the True, Ancient, Catholick and Apoſtolick Faith and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Chriſts Church.</p>
            <p>The whole and only deſign of this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe is, to make Men throughly ſenſible of the Foul and Horrid nature of this days ſin; that if any chance to hear me, who were either
<hi>Actors,</hi> or <hi>Acceſſeries</hi> in it they<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> may joyn with us in ſuch) a ſincere and hearty ſorrow for the Excerable Murder, as may both anſwer the ends of all thoſe judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which we have already felt; and may be a means to prevent thoſe further Scour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:93422:22"/> which we have reaſon yet to Fear.</p>
            <p>Before God and the World I confeſs my ſelf abundantly ſatisfied, that <hi>Popiſh Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites</hi> were in that Horrid Plot, to execute which ſome <hi>Proteſtant Jeſuites</hi> were the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments and Hands. That Roman Prieſt and Confeſſor is known, (ſaith my Author)<note place="margin">Anſwer to <hi>Philanax,</hi> p. 58.</note> who when he ſaw the fatal ſtroke given to our Holy King, flouriſht with his Sword, and ſaid, now the greateſt Enemy that we have in the World is gone: And when the news of that Horrible Execution came to
<hi>Roan</hi> ſome Jeſuited perſons there told a Proteſtant Gentleman (of good credit) that now they were Revenged upon the King of <hi>England,</hi> for not re-eſtabliſhing the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Religion: And much more to the ſame effect we have in the anſwer to <hi>Phila<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But yet it is too too manifeſt, who they were and what they profeſt, who were the
<hi>actual</hi> Regicides. And I will take this juſt oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion from hence to warn all well meaning perſons who profeſs the Reformed Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that they take great care, how they ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer themſelves to be <hi>Abus'd</hi> for the future, or be drawn into the guilt of
<hi>Diſloyalty</hi> or <hi>Reſiſtance.</hi> For I am perſwaded, when our late troubles were upon breaking out,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:93422:23"/> many (even Hot) Men did not look as far as the Scaffold, or dream that it would be built for the King at his own Palace door, but would have abhorr'd the very thoughts and ſuſpicion of it. Many ſpecious and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular <hi>pretences</hi> ran up and down the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and thoſe ſet on foot by the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> themſelves; that <hi>innovations crept into the Church,</hi> that <hi>the Prelates were Popiſhly-af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected,</hi> that there was <hi>great danger of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary Power,</hi> and the like. All the Hiſtories of thoſe times do bear witneſs to the truth of this. But would to God all Sober and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Men would conſider, whither thoſe things came <hi>at laſt.</hi> Did they not end in the ſlaughter of the beſt of Kings? Was not that the Period and ſad concluſion of all? Did not all the clamours and ſtrivings of the people end in that? all actions &amp; proceedings, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever otherwiſe intended by ſome; all was at laſt unhappily Sealed up<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with that blood, which ever ſince has cryed aloud for Venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance upon this Nation. Men ought to be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and wary for the future, and endeavour to choke the <hi>beginnings</hi> of Miſchief.</p>
            <p>For if once the bank be cut, who can tell how far the Deluge will run? In the late times, it was not the <hi>Firſt Intentions,</hi> but
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:93422:23"/> the ſubſequent deſigns of Men, which took place ſo, that after the effuſion of ſo much <hi>Heroick, Noble,</hi> and at laſt <hi>Royal</hi> Blood too, God plagued people ſtrait for their Firſt Reſiſtance; he ſuffered the <hi>Baſeſt</hi> of Men to ride over our backs; he brought us under the very Faeces and Scum of the Nation; and permitted ſuch to be our Lords, as a Man of <hi>Honour</hi> would have diſdained to have ſet
<hi>with the Dogs of his flock,</hi> as the expreſſion is, <hi>Job</hi> 30. 1. And what was the end of this? Why, nothing but Tyranny, Hypocriſie, and Oppreſſion. To uphold Religion they introduced Atheiſm: To promote Arbitrary Power they baniſht our Laws; and to preſerve our Liberties, they made us Slaves, and the very <hi>worſt</hi> of Slaves, Slaves to the
<hi>vileſt</hi> of our <hi>Fellow-ſubjects.</hi> In a word; it may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to be conſider'd, whether all thoſe grievances which People have complain'd of all along under the Kings of <hi>England</hi> (putting them all together) ſince the Conqueſt, do amount to half the value and num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of thoſe Cruelties, Miſeries, and Oppreſſions, which within the compaſs of a few years were brought upon us, by thoſe few Carrion Members, of that one Rake-Hell Parliament of curſed Memory.</p>
            <p>Thus it is, when Men will be Arbitrary, and deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſe the Laws. To affirm (ſaith my Author) that the Kings Power is ſeparable from his Perſon, is High Treaſon by the Law of this Land. And he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves out of the caſe of the two <hi>Spencers</hi> in the Reign of <hi>Edw.</hi> 2. that to cover their Treaſon, they went upon three principles; <hi>1st.</hi> That if the King do not demean himſelf by Reaſon in the right of his Crown, his Subjects are bound by Oath to remove him. <hi>2ly.</hi> That ſeeing the King could not be reformed by ſute at Law, that ought to be done by Force. <hi>3ly.</hi> That his Lieges are bound to govern in aid of him, and in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:93422:24"/> of him. <hi>Jenkins Rediv. Vindic.</hi> Pag. 74.</p>
            <p>Theſe Principles were condemned as Execrable and Deteſtable by two ſeveral Parliaments in thoſe days: And yet theſe were the Fundamental Principles on which that Lewd and Profligate Party did rely in 41. Then, what had been adjudged to be <hi>Execrable</hi> before, paſſed for
<hi>Law</hi> and for <hi>Goſpel</hi> too: Then Treaſon was their <hi>Conſcience,</hi> Reſiſtance was their <hi>Creed,</hi> V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>es and Ordinances their <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> the Sword was their <hi>Judg,</hi> and hence it followed, that ſo many of the Repreſentatives of our Nation was our <hi>greateſt Grievance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God would not ſtay till <hi>Dooms-day</hi> to reckon with us; but his Judgments purſued us cloſe at <hi>heels:</hi> We had <hi>Worm-Wood</hi> for loathing <hi>Manna,</hi> and a Yoke of Bondage upon us, for a Stubborn and Ungovernable humour under a Light hand.</p>
            <p>This was part of our Reward in this World; and ſhould God add weight to our Burthen yet, Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous people muſt confeſs (if they will ever ſpeak Truth in earneſt) that they have deſerved the moſt intole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable of all Evils<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if our Apoſtle be in the night, <hi>that They that Reſiſt, ſhall receive to themſelves Damni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To prevent the Execution of this ſad ſentence,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> all ſuch as have a Real and True value of their Souls, and deſire to live ſo in this world, as not to he miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in another, let ſuch account Subjection to the King, both an <hi>Honourable</hi> and a <hi>Neceſſary</hi> part o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Religion, and not ſuffer themſelves either to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wheadled out of their Loyalty by
<hi>Flatteries,</hi> or to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:93422:24"/> huſſt out of it by <hi>Fears.</hi> Methinks 'tis ſomething odd, that when we all agree in the Premiſes, we ſhould differ in the Concluſion. That Kings ought to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted unto, is a Truth aſſented to by all ſober Chriſtians in the World; This is owned in general. The miſchief is, that when we come to Particulars (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Things or Perſons) either prejudice, or paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, or intereſts of Men, ſtart Evaſions, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, which were never heard of in the World a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Chriſtians before. Some are for the King, as long as he is Rich, Powerful, and able to maintain their Intereſt; that's the Loyalty of the <hi>Leviathan.</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſtick to <hi>him,</hi> as long as he ſticks to their
<hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion;</hi> that is, the Loyalty of the <hi>Conclave,</hi> and the <hi>Kirk.</hi> But the Faith of the Church of <hi>England</hi> is this (which I am ſure is conſonant to the univerſal ſenſe and practice of the Ancient, Apoſtolick Church, that let Princes be (as it ſhall pleaſe God) either a <hi>Bleſſing,</hi> or a <hi>Rod</hi> to a Kingdom, in all things
<hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> they are to be <hi>Obeyed;</hi> and where we cannot Obey <hi>them,</hi> but by ſinning againſt <hi>God,</hi> there their Authority is to be <hi>ſubmitted unto;</hi> ſo that whatever their <hi>Practices,</hi> or their <hi>Faith</hi> be, yet their
<hi>Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives,</hi> their <hi>Perſons,</hi> their <hi>Lives</hi> muſt be <hi>Sacred:</hi> though they be <hi>Sauls,</hi> yet 'tis a moſt <hi>fearful</hi> thing to lift up ones hand to deſtroy the Lords Anointed. I ſhall conclude all with that of the wiſeſt of Monarchs and Men, <hi>Prov. 24. 21. My Son, fear thou the Lord, and the King, and meddle not with them that are given to change. Amen,</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>Soli Deo Gratia.</trailer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
